# Yinan (Tom) Xuan

yxuan@ucsd.edu https://www.yinanxuan.com My research interests lie at the intersection of ubiquitous computing, personal tracking, and HCI. I am interested in passive sensing for human activities and physiological status. I am trying to achieve this goal by leveraging both machine learning and my prototyping skills in both software and hardware.

### EDUCATION

# University of California, San Diego

La Jolla, CA

Ph.D. in Electrical & Computer Engineering

July 2020 - June 2024 (exp.)

Advisor: Edward Wang

Areas: Ubiquitous Health Sensing

M.S. in Biological Science Sept. 2017 – June 2020

Advisor: Jing Wang

Thesis: Computer Vision Aided Drosophila Gut Imaging Data Collection and Analysis

B.S. in Physiology & Neuroscience Sept. 2013 – June 2017

Minor: Cognitive Science Honors: MAGNA CUM LAUDE (GPA 3.89/4.00)

#### EXPERIENCE

# Graduate Research Assistant

Oct. 2019 - Present

La Jolla, CA

University of California, San Diego

Electrical and Computer Engineering Department, Jacobs School of Engineering DigiHealth Lab

- Designed and built an ultra low-cost blood pressure monitoring smartphone device consisted of flexible 3D-printed hardware accessories and on-device ML/OpenCV Android application.
- Designed and implemented SpecTracle, a vision-based unobtrusive facial tracking system for AR, which consists of fisheye lens cameras controlled by Raspberry Pi and an image based neural network model.
- Implemented a Unity exercising game prototype that uses IMU signals on Vuzix AR glasses
- Built a mini compression testing machine that can test various materials and designs of gadgets used in ubiquitous computing.

# Indie Game Developer

June 2021 – Present

- Project Management: Coordinated among team members and made decisions about development details and timeline.
- Development: Built all elements in the game with C# in Unity 2D, including but not limited to: Items, Quests, Dialogues, and Cut Scenes.
- Gameplay Design: Designed player experience and overall gameplay system.
- Technical Art: Designed and built VFXs with 2D lighting, shader graphs and particle system.

#### Graduate Research Assistant

April 2018 – June 2020

University of California, San Diego

La Jolla, CA

Section of Neurobiology, Division of Biological Science

Wang Lab

- $\bullet$  Designed and implemented an olfaction VR device as a novel instrument to observe odor guided behaviors in Drosophila
- Designed, implemented and deployed an image processing software to facilitate bio-imaging data analysis pipeline that profiles *Drosophila* intestinal cells' response to different nutrients.
- Designed, implemented and deployed an automated solenoid valve control system for perfusion experiments that can independently control up to 22 valves.
- Collaborated in building and testing a customized three-photon fluorescent imaging microscope.
- Built a feedback controlled temperature-based anesthetic platform to facilitate surgery process on *Drosophila*.

### Undergraduate Researcher Assistant

University of California, San Diego

Division of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, Department of Surgery Ongkeko Lab

Advisor: Weg Ongkeko

Jan 2014 – June 2017

• Studied the role of long non-coding RNAs in head and neck squamous cell cancer.

• Designed and conducted in vitro experiments for various projects.

### Research Internship

June 2016 – Aug. 2016

 $Camarillo,\ CA$ 

La Jolla, CA

AskGene Pharmaceutical Inc.

• Collaborated in cell line development selecting clone cells with the highest titer.

• Purified recombinant antibodies using Protein-A Affinity Chromatography.

# SKILLS

#### Software

Languages: Python, Matlab, C#, C++, Kotlin, Java, JavaScript, SQL (MySQL)

Machine Learning Models: Neural Networks, SVM, Hierarchical Clustering, DBSCAN, Gaussian Mixture Model, etc.

Data Analysis/Preprocessing: Dimension Reduction, Signal Processing, Computer Vision / Image Processing, etc.

Mobile Development: iOS (Swift), Android (Kotlin/JAVA)

Web Development: HTML/CSS, Bootstrap, React, Node.js

#### Hardware

 $Rapid\ Prototyping:\ Solid Works,\ 3D\ printing\ with\ SLA/FDM\ using\ rigid/flexible\ material,\ laser\ cutting\ printing\ printing\$ 

Embedded System Prototyping: PCB design, micro-controller programming, Prototype w/ Raspberry Pi

Free-space Optics

Compressed Gas Cylinder Handling

#### Biotech

Animal Handling: Mice, Drosophila, C. elegans

Benchwork: cell culture, RNA extraction, qRT-PCR, transfection, etc.

### Publications

# • Papers under Review

1. **Xuan, Y.**, Viswanath, V., Chu, S., Bartolf, O., Echterhoff, J., Wang, E. *SpecTracle: Wearable Facial Motion Tracking from Unobstructing Peripheral Cameras* 

### • Peer-Reviewed Publications

- 2. Barry, C., Souza, J., **Xuan, Y.**, Holden, J., Granholm, E., Wang, E. *Enabling Smartphone Pupillometry using a Facial Identification Camera in At-Home Environments*. **CHI 2022** (accepted but not yet published)
- 3. Lin, H.-H., Kuang, M. C., Hossain, I., **Xuan, Y.**, Beebe, L., Shepherd, A. K., Rolandi, M., Wang, J. W. (2022). A nutrient-specific gut hormone arbitrates between courtship and feeding. In **Nature**. Springer Science and Business Media LLC. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-022-04408-7
- Yu, V., Rahimy, M., Korrapati, A., Xuan, Y., Zou, A. E., Krishnan, A. R., Tsui, T., Aguilera, J. A., Advani, S., Crotty Alexander, L. E., Brumund, K. T., Wang-Rodriguez, J., amp; Ongkeko, W. M. (2016). Electronic cigarettes induce DNA strand breaks and cell death independently of nicotine in cell lines. Oral Oncology, 52, 58–65. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.oraloncology.2015.10.018
- Zou, A. E., Ku, J., Honda, T. K., Yu, V., Kuo, S. Z., Zheng, H., Xuan, Y., Saad, M. A., Hinton, A., Brumund, K. T., Lin, J. H., Wang-Rodriguez, J., amp; Ongkeko, W. M. (2015). Transcriptome sequencing uncovers novel long noncoding and small nucleolar RNAs dysregulated in head and neck squamous cell carcinoma. RNA, 21(6), 1122–1134. https://doi.org/10.1261/rna.049262.114

Zou, A. E., Zheng, H., Saad, M. A., Rahimy, M., Ku, J., Kuo, S. Z., Honda, T. K., Wang-Rodriguez, J., Xuan, Y., Korrapati, A., Yu, V., Singh, P., Grandis, J. R., King, C. C., Lippman, S. M., Wang, X. Q., Hinton, A., amp; Ongkeko, W. M. (2016). The non-coding landscape of head and neck squamous cell carcinoma. Oncotarget, 7(32), 51211–51222. https://doi.org/10.18632/oncotarget.9979

#### • Posters

- Zou, A. E., Krishnan, A. R., Xuan, Y., Saad, M. A., Korrapati, A., Advani, S. J., Wang-Rodriguez, J., amp; Ongkeko, W. (2016). Abstract 977: RNA-sequencing analysis implicates novel non-coding RNAs in human papillomavirus-associated head and neck squamous cell carcinoma. Molecular and Cellular Biology, Genetics. https://doi.org/10.1158/1538-7445.am2016-977
- 8. Korrapati, A., Yu, V., Saad, M. A., Rahimy, M., **Xuan, Y.**, Zou, A., Krishnan, A., Brumund, K., amp; Ongkeko, W. M. (2016). Abstract 4069: *The carcinogenic effects of electronic cigarettes in oral cancer*. Tumor Biology. https://doi.org/10.1158/1538-7445.am2016-4069
- 9. Ku, J., Zou, A. E., Honda, T. K., Zheng, H., Saad, M. A., Yu, V., **Xuan, Y.**, Singh, P., Rahimy, M., Kuo, S. Z., Ongkeko, W. M., amp; Wang-Rodriguez, J. (2015). Abstract 3836: *Identification of key survival-correlating microRNAs and Piwi-interacting RNAs dysregulated in head and neck squamous cell carcinoma*. Molecular and Cellular Biology. https://doi.org/10.1158/1538-7445.am2015-3836
- Honda, T. K., Zou, A., Yu, V., Zheng, H., Kuo, S., Saad, M., Xuan, Y., Singh, P., Wang-Rodriguez, J., amp; Ongkeko, W. M. (2015). Abstract 151: Transcriptome-wide expression profiling of long noncoding and small nucleolar RNAs in head and neck squamous cell carcinomas identifies novel transcripts associated with survival. Molecular and Cellular Biology. https://doi.org/10.1158/1538-7445.am2015-151

### TEACHING AND MENTORING EXPERIENCE

# Teaching Assistant

2018 Fall - UCSD BIPN 100 Human Physiology I

# Mentorship

- 2021 MAE student team, undergraduate capstone project
- 2020 Sunny Chu, undergraduate researcher from UCSD ECE department
- 2020 Owen Bartolf, undergraduate researcher from UCSD CSE department

#### SERVICE

• Reviewer for UbiComp/ISWC 2020 Posters and Demos

### Membership & Honors

- Member of Phi Beta Kappa Honor Society
- Member of Muir College's Senior Honors Caledonian Society

#### Languages

- Madarin Native Speaker
- English Professional
- Japanese Daily Communication (JLPT N2 Equivalent)
- Cantonese Daily Communication